[Speaker 1] Okay. I'm not pretty sure because I've never been to one or already, but I would
[발화자 1] 네. 확실하진 않아요, 왜냐하면 한 번도 가본 적이 없거나 이미 가봤거나 해서요, 하지만 저는
try to get some help out of someone, right? That could help me because I'm an elderly person. So
누군가에게 도움을 청하려고 할 거예요, 그렇죠? 저를 도와줄 수 있는 사람이요, 왜냐하면 저는 나이가 많은 사람이니까요. 그래서
[Speaker 1] it's, things are more difficult for us than to a young person. So I would.
[발화자 1] 저희 같은 사람들에게는 젊은 사람들보다 상황이 더 어렵거든요. 그래서 저는 그럴 거예요.
[Speaker 2] We call for help. You would call someone on your phone where we could call out for help.
[발화자 2] 도움을 요청하시겠군요. 전화로 누군가에게 연락하거나 도움을 요청할 수 있겠죠.
[Speaker 1] Yeah. Yeah. If that was a situation, I call for help actually. Yeah.
[발화자 1] 네. 네. 만약 그런 상황이라면, 저는 실제로 도움을 요청할 거예요. 네.
Well, you can say help. Help just to get me out of the flood.
음, "도와주세요"라고 말할 수 있겠죠. "도와주세요, 홍수에서 저 좀 꺼내주세요."라고요.
[Speaker 1] You know, the thing is like, it's like static in there because that's a tunnel and it has,
[발화자 1] 아시다시피, 그건 마치, 그 안이 정체된 것 같아요, 왜냐하면 그건 터널이고, 그 터널은
at the very end of it, it has to like higher points. So the flood comes right in between
맨 끝부분에 더 높은 지점들이 있거든요. 그래서 홍수가 바로 그 사이로
[Speaker 1] into the tunnel and out the tunnel. [Speaker 2] It's like a pool of water.
[발화자 1] 터널 안으로 들어왔다가 터널 밖으로 나가요. [발화자 2] 마치 물웅덩이 같네요.
[Speaker 1] Yeah. It wasn't like a pool that you can actually go and swim. Yeah. I will have hope. I will ask
[발화자 1] 네. 실제로 가서 수영할 수 있는 그런 수영장 같은 건 아니었어요. 네. 저는 희망을 가질 거예요. 저는 실제로
for help actually. That's what I would do, you know, or maybe if I can, if I cannot find help,
도움을 요청할 거예요. 그게 제가 할 일이죠, 아시잖아요, 아니면 혹시 제가 도움을 찾을 수 없다면,
[Speaker 1] I will start running and trying to grab things around me so I'm not to get, you know, in the
[발화자 1] 저는 달리기 시작해서 주변의 것들을 붙잡으려고 할 거예요, 그래서 제가, 아시다시피, 홍수에
flood and try to escape from there. [Speaker 2] If it flooded, I would swim because I know how to swim,
휩쓸리지 않도록 하고 거기서 탈출하려고 할 거예요. [발화자 2] 만약 홍수가 났다면, 저는 수영을 할 거예요, 왜냐하면 저는 수영을 할 줄 알거든요.
but do you know how to swim? [Speaker 1] Just a little bit. I get cramps whenever I try to swim, so
하지만 학생분은 수영할 줄 아시나요? [발화자 1] 조금요. 수영하려고 할 때마다 쥐가 나서요, 그래서
I'm not trying to do so because that comes terrible. [Speaker 2] If you don't have to, you wouldn't try.
그렇게 하려고 하지 않아요, 왜냐하면 그건 끔찍한 일이 되거든요. [발화자 2] 꼭 해야 하는 상황이 아니라면 시도하지 않으시겠군요.
[Speaker 1] Yeah. And especially the water, the flood, I mean, it's kind of nasty in that part.
[발화자 1] 네. 특히 그 물, 홍수 말이에요, 그 부분은 좀 지저분해요.
All the people from some parts of the city, they are thrown to that part. So I don't,
도시 일부 지역의 모든 사람들이 그쪽으로 버려지거든요. 그래서 저는,
[Speaker 1] it's not recommendable. [Speaker 2] I think a better hypothetical situation would be to be in a
[발화자 1] 추천할 만하지 않아요. [발화자 2] 제 생각엔 더 나은 가상 상황은 가족과 함께 좋은 곳에 있는 것일 거예요.
good place with your family, someplace where you're safe and just going to get food to eat.
안전하고 그냥 먹을 음식을 구하러 가는 곳에요.
[Speaker 2] That sounds like the perfect hypothetical situation.
[발화자 2] 그게 완벽한 가상 상황처럼 들리네요.
[Speaker 1] Yeah, I wish I could be safer than that.
[발화자 1] 네, 저도 그것보다 더 안전했으면 좋겠어요.
[Speaker 2] Here's a question here. We've looked at some general conversation starters
[발화자 2] 여기 질문이 하나 있습니다. 우리는 몇 가지 일반적인 대화 시작 표현들과
and hypothetical questions. Let's try to connect these to your own thoughts
가상 질문들을 살펴봤습니다. 이것들을 학생분의 생각과
[Speaker 2] and potential conversations, things that you'd like to talk about.
[발화자 2] 잠재적인 대화, 즉 이야기하고 싶은 것들과 연결해 봅시다.
So we can look back at these conversation starters that we've had and the hypothetical
그래서 우리가 했던 이 대화 시작 표현들과 가상 질문들을 다시 살펴보고,
[Speaker 2] questions and try to think about the most interesting types of questions and how we
[발화자 2] 가장 흥미로운 유형의 질문들과 실제 대화에서 다른 질문에 어떻게 답할 수 있을지
might answer another one in a real conversation. What type of situations would you use these types
생각해 볼 수 있습니다. 어떤 유형의 상황에서 이런 종류의 질문들을 사용하시겠어요?
[Speaker 2] of questions? Let's try to categorize this a little bit more. Previously, I showed you a list
[발화자 2] 이것을 좀 더 분류해 봅시다. 이전에, 제가 여기 이 다른 질문들의 목록을
here of these different questions. The first question says, what's the most interesting
보여드렸죠. 첫 번째 질문은 "지금까지 방문했던 곳 중 가장 흥미로운 곳은 어디이며,
[Speaker 2] place you've ever visited and what made it special? If you answered that question there,
[발화자 2] 무엇이 그곳을 특별하게 만들었나요?"입니다. 만약 그 질문에 답하셨다면,
when would you ask this question in a conversation? [Speaker 1] What kind of situation?
대화 중에 언제 이 질문을 하시겠어요? [발화자 1] 어떤 종류의 상황에서요?
Well, I would like to ask somebody that I recently met. We start a conversation
음, 저는 최근에 만난 사람에게 물어보고 싶어요. 우리가 대화를 시작할 때,
[Speaker 1] just like an icebreaking thing, right? And just to break the ice, I would start a conversation
[발화자 1] 마치 어색함을 깨는 것처럼요, 그렇죠? 그리고 그냥 어색함을 깨기 위해, 저는 대화를 시작할 거예요.
telling, well, if I see that they're interested in that type of conversation.
음, 만약 그들이 그런 종류의 대화에 관심이 있다는 것을 안다면요.
[Speaker 1] But, you know, it's like a very common thing to do, to talk about yourself when you're being
[발화자 1] 하지만, 아시다시피, 자신에 대해 이야기하는 것은 매우 흔한 일이죠, 누군가에게 소개받거나
introduced or introducing yourself to somebody, right? And you're looking for questions or,
자신을 소개할 때요, 그렇죠? 그리고 질문거리나, 아시다시피,
[Speaker 1] you know, history that you can tell. [Speaker 2] It's great to have a question that
[발화자 1] 말할 수 있는 이야기거리를 찾고 있을 때요. [발화자 2] 답변할 수 있는 질문이 있다는 것은 좋습니다.
you can answer because then you know what you can say. But it helps the other person,
왜냐하면 그러면 무엇을 말할 수 있는지 알 수 있으니까요. 하지만 상대방에게도 도움이 됩니다,
[Speaker 2] too, if you can ask them a question like this as well. It makes the conversation go
[발화자 2] 만약 당신도 그들에게 이런 질문을 할 수 있다면요. 그것은 대화를 더
smoother. They go both ways as well. [Speaker 1] Yeah. And especially that question that I answered,
원활하게 만듭니다. 양쪽 모두에게 효과가 있죠. [발화자 1] 네. 특히 제가 답했던 그 질문,
which is the first one, because, you know, you start talking about your working places,
첫 번째 질문이요, 왜냐하면, 아시다시피, 직장에 대해 이야기하기 시작하잖아요,
[Speaker 1] right? And if they tell me, where have I worked? So I tell them in the airport.
[발화자 1] 그렇죠? 그리고 만약 그들이 저에게 어디서 일했냐고 물으면, 저는 공항에서 일했다고 말해요.
So they ask me if I got to travel a lot, because being an airport employee,
그래서 그들은 제가 여행을 많이 다녔는지 물어보죠, 왜냐하면 공항 직원이니까요,
[Speaker 1] they start asking things like that. I used to work for a very small airline,
[발화자 1] 그런 것들을 물어보기 시작해요. 저는 아주 작은 항공사에서 일했었어요,
right, that works only, flights only locally here within the country. So I used to talk about
그렇죠, 그 항공사는 여기 국내에서만, 국내선만 운항해요. 그래서 저는
[Speaker 1] our islands, San Pedro Sula, which is a northern point place here in the country. And that's just
[발화자 1] 우리나라 섬들이나, 산 페드로 술라, 여기 북쪽에 있는 곳에 대해 이야기하곤 했어요. 그리고 그건 그냥
to break the ice and start a conversation. I usually, or talking about their family,
어색함을 깨고 대화를 시작하기 위한 것이죠. 저는 보통, 아니면 그들의 가족에 대해 이야기하거나,
[Speaker 1] where they're from, and all that kind of stuff. Just to break the ice. That's always the same
[발화자 1] 어디 출신인지, 그리고 그런 종류의 모든 것들에 대해 이야기해요. 그냥 어색함을 깨기 위해서요. 항상 똑같아요.
thing. [Speaker 2] This is something that you're really comfortable with yourself. You've had these
이런 것들이요. [발화자 2] 이것은 학생분이 스스로에게 매우 편안하게 느끼는 부분이군요. 이런 대화들을
conversations a lot in English. So if we need to step outside of the comfort zone a little bit,
영어로 많이 해보셨군요. 그래서 만약 우리가 안전지대에서 조금 벗어날 필요가 있다면,
[Speaker 2] maybe we could ask another one of these questions. Okay. If you could choose another
[발화자 2] 아마도 이 질문들 중 다른 하나를 물어볼 수 있을 겁니다. 네. 만약 첫 번째 질문 외에 다른 질문을
question besides the first one, which question would you choose? And when would you ask this
선택하신다면, 어떤 질문을 선택하시겠어요? 그리고 언제 이 질문을 하시겠어요?
[Speaker 2] question? [Speaker 1] Okay. Let me just read them back again. Tell me about a challenge you overcame.
[발화자 2] [발화자 1] 네. 다시 한번 읽어볼게요. 극복했던 도전에 대해 말해주세요.
What did you learn from it? What's something you're looking forward to in the near future?
그것으로부터 무엇을 배웠나요? 가까운 미래에 기대하고 있는 것은 무엇인가요?
[Speaker 1] What hobby or activity do you enjoy that others might find surprising? Okay. One of the things
[발화자 1] 다른 사람들이 놀랄 만한 취미나 활동은 무엇인가요? 네. 그중 하나는
is just to get a new job. That's one of my challenges, because even if I'm an elderly
새로운 직업을 구하는 것입니다. 그것이 제 도전 중 하나예요, 왜냐하면 제가 나이가 많은 사람이지만,
[Speaker 1] person, but I need to support myself. I'm not used to being supported by somebody else.
[발화자 1] 제 자신을 부양해야 하거든요. 저는 다른 사람에게 부양받는 것에 익숙하지 않아요.
I've always been a provider, so I need to get me a job myself. And it's been hard and challenging
저는 항상 부양자였어요, 그래서 제 스스로 직업을 구해야 해요. 그리고 그건 저에게 힘들고 도전적이었어요,
[Speaker 1] to me, because as I told you, I'm an elderly person, and you know, possibilities in my country,
[발화자 1] 왜냐하면 말씀드렸듯이, 저는 나이가 많은 사람이고, 아시다시피, 제 나라에서는 저 같은 사람이나
there are not too many for people like me or somebody else my same age and things like that.
제 또래의 다른 사람들을 위한 기회가 그렇게 많지 않거든요, 그런 것들이요.
[Speaker 1] But, you know, the more prepared I am, the faster I'll get a job, right? But even if you study a lot
[발화자 1] 하지만, 아시다시피, 제가 더 잘 준비될수록, 더 빨리 직업을 구할 수 있겠죠, 그렇죠? 하지만 때로는 많이 공부하고
sometimes and you have a lot of experience, that's not enough in this country, because
경험이 많아도, 이 나라에서는 그것만으로는 충분하지 않아요, 왜냐하면
[Speaker 1] you've got a lot of competition with younger people well prepared for the kind of job that
[발화자 1] 우리가 지원할 수 있는 종류의 직업에 대해 잘 준비된 젊은 사람들과의 경쟁이 치열하거든요.
we might be applying for. [Speaker 2] I'm really sorry to hear that it's been so challenging.
[발화자 2] 그렇게 힘들었다니 정말 안타깝네요.
I know in many places it's a challenge for elderly people to find equal opportunities.
많은 곳에서 연장자들이 동등한 기회를 찾는 것이 어렵다는 것을 알고 있습니다.
[Speaker 2] But just after talking with you a few times for a few classes, I can really tell that you have
[발화자 2] 하지만 몇 번의 수업을 통해 학생분과 몇 번 대화한 후, 저는 학생분이 정말로
some awesome communication skills. You have some impressive experience. And if I were an employer,
훌륭한 의사소통 기술을 가지고 있다는 것을 알 수 있습니다. 인상적인 경험도 가지고 계시고요. 만약 제가 고용주라면,
[Speaker 2] I would really be interested in your resume and your experience. You have a lot of great things
[발화자 2] 학생분의 이력서와 경험에 정말 관심이 많을 겁니다. 학생분은 제공할 수 있는 훌륭한 것들이 많고,
to offer and might have problems finding opportunities in Honduras, but I don't think
온두라스에서 기회를 찾는 데 어려움이 있을지 모르지만, 저는 학생분이
[Speaker 2] you would have any type of problem finding opportunities in other places. I think you
[발화자 2] 다른 곳에서 기회를 찾는 데 어떤 종류의 문제도 없을 거라고 생각합니다. 제 생각엔 학생분은
do it. You just have to believe in yourself. We have some really wonderful skills and communication
해낼 수 있어요. 그저 자신을 믿기만 하면 됩니다. 정말 훌륭한 기술과 의사소통 기술을 가지고 계세요.
[Speaker 2] skills. I'm so impressed by your ability to put things into words.
[발화자 2] 생각을 말로 표현하는 능력에 정말 감탄했습니다.